你好黑客
hello hackers
今天我们要讲的是
today we're going to be talking about
格式字符串和格式字符串漏洞
format strings and format string vulnerabilities
格式字符串漏洞存在于许多函数中
now format string vulnerabilities exist in a number of functions
但是我们今天要看的函数是printf
but the function that we're going to look at today is printf
这是，在讨论这类漏洞时，最常讲的函数
which is the common case that is used when discussing these type of vulnerabilities
printf是怎么用的呢
so how does printf work
printf可接受可变数量的参数
well printf can take a variable number of arguments
第一个参数是一个格式化字符串
the first argument is considered a format string
你可以直接给printf传一个hello这样的字符串
now you could just pass printf with a string like printf hello
这将输出hello到标准输出
and this would display hello to standard out
但printf通常都会和其它参数一起使用
but printf is typically used with some additional arguments
这些其它参数
and these additional arguments
是你想要按格式并替换到格式化字符串中的值
are the values that you want to be formatted and kind of substituted in the format string
看一下第二个例子
so if we look at the second example here
是 Hello %s   name
we have hello percent s name
这里的name应该是一个字符串
now name should be in this case a string
假设它的值是：pwn.college
so let's say it's pwn college
这里printf的执行结果
the result of calling printf percent s name
将是 Hello pwn.college
would be Hello Pwn College
printf会把%s，这个速记，替换成字符串值，即name
and printf is going to substitute that percent shorthand of percent s with the string value that is name
在第三个例子中
in the third example
能看到可以替换的不仅仅是字符串
we see that we can substitute things that are not just strings
还能替换整数和浮点数
but even integer values or floats right
这里的 %d lights ,5
so there are percent d lights 5
这里将会把整数5转换成数字5的字符
this is going to take the integer 5 convert it to the number 5 as a string
然后替换掉%d
and then substitute that in for percent d
正如在第四个例子中看到的，printf可以替换多个值
now printf can do this for multiple values which is what we see in the fourth example
The average of %d, %d, %d is %f
the average of percent d percent d and percent d is percent f
格式化字符串外的前三个参数是整数
the first three additional arguments passed in are integers
第4个是浮点数
and the fourth argument is in fact a float
printf会处理好这些不同数据类型的值
and printf will take care of formatting these distinct data types
然后把它们插入到格式化字符串中合适的位置
and inserting them into the string in the appropriate location
用起来很方便
and that this is a very handy thing to have
但printf怎么知道应有多少参数的
but how does printf know how many arguments there should be
printf盲目地相信格式化字符串中的记号
well printf just blindly trusts the format string that initial argument
那么，如果用户控制了格式化字符串呢
so what happens if the user controls the format string value
我们能创建任意多的%记号
we could have an arbitrary number of these percent shorthands
事情可能会变得有点失控
and things could get a little out of hand
格式化字符串决定了printf期待的参数
so the format string determines what arguments printf is expecting
那这些参数都存在哪里呢
but where are these arguments located
printf可以接受任意数量的参数
if printf can take an arbitrary number of arguments
它是否遵循我们已知的标准调用约定呢
does it follow the same standard calling convention that we already know
这些例子中，参数都是对应好的
in these examples everything kind of lines up
在 hello % s 中
we have printf hello percent s
我们只给了一个字符串name参数
and we give it one argument name which is a string
但是如果我们
but what happens if we say
在格式化字符串中写入大量的%s
hello percent s percent s percent s and we keep passing percent s
占用所有x64调用约定规定的寄存器
eventually we're going to run out of registers right
但我们没有传入足够的参数给printf
if we don't pass enough arguments to the function
它仍然要试着找到对应的值
it's still going to have to try and find that value
来替换%s
it's going to have to find something to substitute percent s with
为了弄明白这个
and so to kind of make sense of this
我们需要深入C代码之下
we have to look a little bit deeper than the C code
会看看调用printf时的汇编代码
and so we're going to take a look at the assembly here when we do call printf
实际上这和我们习惯的调用约定没有不同
because there isn't in fact a different calling convention than what we are used to
我们熟悉的调用约定会按顺序用到 RDI RSI RDX RCX R8 R9
we should be familiar with the standard calling convention of RDI RSI RDX rcx r8 R9
但若要传递更多参数，来替换到格式化字符串中
but what happens if we need to have more values to substitute into the format string
这些参数存储在哪里
where these values located
答案就是：栈
it turns out it's on the stack
我们来看一看
let's take a look
为了探索这个问题，我们要
to explore this what we're going to do is
我们创建一个C文件
we're going to make a C file
调用printf
and we are going to call printf
然后在GDB中查看
and then take a look at it in GDB
看看到底发生了什么
to see what is going on under the hood
我们 include
so we'll include stdio.h
这是调用printf的必要条件
which is necessary to call printf
这里写一个标准的main函数
we'll do a kind of a standard main function here
参数是argc和argv
with argc and argv
我们将调用printf，带7个整数
we're going to call printf uh 7 integers
把整数命名为a到g
we will just name the integers a through g
我们让它们递增1
and we will make each one of them a slightly higher number
然后把它们传给printf
and we'll pass each one of them to printf
所以我们会看到1 2 3 4 5 6 7
so we would expect to see 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
我们编译并运行它
so let's compile this and run it
我们看到了1 2 3 4 5 6 7
we do see 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
但在末尾有些垃圾数据
but we have some kind of garbage here at the end
这是因为没在末尾加上换行符
and that is because we are not ending this with a new line
我们再来一次
so if we do that again
现在干净了，能看到1到7
now it is clean and we see 1 through 7 as expected
所以底层到底放生了什么呢？
so what's happening under the hood
我们在GDB中打开它
we open this up in GDB
反汇编一下main
we can disassemble the main function
我们想看看
and we want to take a look at
跳转到printf前，是如何设置参数的
how are these arguments set up before we go into printf
能看到printf在这里被调用
and we see printf is called right here
我们在main + 115处设置一个断点
so we'll set a breakpoint at main plus 115
运行它
we run it
我们看看寄存器里都有啥
let's take a look at what's in the registers
基于我们已知的调用约定
now based upon our kind of existing knowledge of calling conventions
我们预计RDI是格式化字符串
we would expect RDI to be the format string
能看到RDI像个地址
and we see that RDI looks like an address
检查一下这个地址的字符串
so let's examine the string at that address
这里确实是格式化字符串
and we do in fact see the format string located there
剩下的参数是a到g
now the remaining arguments a through G
按照调用约定
we follow through calling conventions
能看到RSI是1，RDX是2，RCX是3，R8是4，R9是5
we see RSI is 1 rdx is 2 RCX is 3 r8 is 4 r9 is 5
现在传给printf的6和7，f和g的值，在哪里
now where are the 6 and 7 the f and g values that are passed in here via printf
如果我们看一些栈上的东西
and if we take a look at what is on the stack
就会看到RSP指向6，RSP+8指向7
we'll see that RSP points to 6 and that RSP+ 8 is 7
这就是printf获取这些值的地方
and so that is where printf is getting these values from
现在我们使用整数
now we used integers
因为在寄存器或内存中找它们的时候
because that was kind of an easy thing to identify
这样比较容易识别
when we're looking at what's in a register or what's sitting in memory
但不一定非得是整数
but it doesn't have to all be integers
printf可以接受各种数据类型
printf can take a variety of data types
只要和格式化字符串中对应就行
as long as you specify it correctly in the format string
如果我们给一个char*
so if we give it a char star
然后传入name，值为pwn.college
give it the name pwn college
在格式化字符串中加入%s换行符
we'll add a % s followed by a new line
把name作为下一个参数传入
and we pass that in right there as the next argument
我们将看到，1到7，换行，pwn.college
so we would expect to see 1 through 7 a new line followed by Pwn College
这就是我们所看到的
and that is in fact what we see
GDB中发生了什么
and what goes on in GDB
设置断点在调用printf之前
set the break point right before printf is called
运行它
we run it
看一下栈
and let's take a look at what is on the stack
这是一个字符串值
this is a string value
所以ASCII字符串本身不在这里
so the ASCII characters themselves aren't located here
这是一个指向字符串的指针
this is a pointer to the string
我们可以查看这个地址处的字符串
so we can examine the string that is at that address
能看到pwn.college
and now we see Pwn College
这引出了printf有意思的一点
and this kind of introduces one of the interesting things about printf is
到目前为止，格式化字符串和参数都是对应的
so far I've specified everything correctly
在一些情况下
in some of the you know
下个视频我们将探讨
next videos we'll explore
如果传递的类型
what happens if the type that is passed
和在格式化字符串中指定的不匹配，会怎样
doesn't match the type that is specified in the format string
令人惊讶的是，这并不罕见
it's surprisingly not that uncommon
传给printf的格式化字符串能被用户控制
for the user to have control of the format string that is then passed to printf
竟是一个常见的错误
it's a pretty common mistake
特别是考虑到内存破坏的存在
especially when you consider scenarios where memory corruption may be at play
通过利用这些格式字符串
and by abusing these format strings
我们可以泄漏甚至控制内存
we can leak and even control memory
这就是格式化字符串漏洞存在所需的全部条件
now this right here is all that it takes for a format string vulnerability to exist
唯一的需求就是用户能控制传给printf的首个参数
the only requirement is that the user has control of that first argument to printf
即，格式化字符串
that format string
能看到
now you'll note that
这里的printf没有传入其它的参数
there are no additional values or arguments being passed to this printf
这是因为printf实际上并不关心
and that's because printf actually doesn't care
printf只是盲目地相信
printf just blindly trusts that
每一个%d，都有一个对应的整数
for every percent d there'll be an integer
每个%s，都有一个对应的字符串
for every percent s there'll be a string
如果我们不在c代码中指出
and if we don't specify it in the c
printf就会查看寄存器或栈上的相关位置
printf is just going to go and check the register or check the location on the stack
假设要的值就在这里
and just assume that the value is there
然后按照格式化字符串解读它
and interpret it as it was intended from the format string
这就是漏洞所在
and that's where the vulnerability lies
有趣的是，printf在循环中是图灵完备的
interestingly printf is turing complete when it's in a while loop
hexhive的这个项目
this project here by hexhive
是brainf**k的一个实现
is an implementation of brain f**k
它基于运行在while循环中的printf
that runs on top of a printf while loop
这绝对是件有趣的事
definitely an interesting thing if you have time
有时间，去看看吧
go check it out